<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc colonspace="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-rtcweb-ip-handling-03"
ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="WebRTC IP Handling">WebRTC IP Address Handling
    Requirements</title>
    <author fullname="Justin Uberti" initials="J." surname="Uberti">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>747 6th St S</street>
          <city>Kirkland</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98033</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>justin@uberti.name</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Guo-wei Shieh" initials="G." surname="Shieh">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>747 6th St S</street>
          <city>Kirkland</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98033</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>guoweis@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date day="14" month="January" year="2017" />
    <area>RAI</area>
    <abstract>
      <t>This document provides information and requirements for how
      IP addresses should be handled by WebRTC applications.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>As a technology that supports peer-to-peer connections, WebRTC may
      send data over different network paths than the path used for HTTP
      traffic. This may allow a web application to learn additional information
      about the user, which may be problematic in certain cases. This document
      summarizes the concerns, and makes recommendations on how best to handle
      the tradeoff between privacy and media performance.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Terminology">

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in
      <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Problem Statement">
      <t>WebRTC enables real-time peer-to-peer communications by enumerating
      network interfaces and discovering the best route through the ICE
      <xref target="RFC5245" />protocol. During the ICE process, the peers
      involved in a session gather and exchange all the IP addresses they can
      discover, so that the connectivity of each IP pair can be checked, and
      the best path chosen. The addresses that are gathered usually consist of
      an endpoint's private physical/virtual addresses, and its public Internet
      addresses.</t>
      <t>These addresses are exposed upwards to the web application, so that
      they can be communicated to the remote endpoint. This allows the
      application to learn more about the local network configuration than it
      would from a typical HTTP scenario, in which the web server would only
      see a single public Internet address, i.e. the address from which the
      HTTP request was sent.</t>
      <t>The information revealed falls into three categories:
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>If the client is behind a NAT, the client's private IP addresses,
        typically
        <xref target="RFC1918" />addresses, can be learned.</t>
        <t>If the client tries to hide its physical location through a VPN, and
        the VPN and local OS support routing over multiple interfaces (i.e., a
        "split-tunnel" VPN), WebRTC will discover the public address for the
        VPN as well as the ISP public address that the VPN runs over.</t>
        <t>If the client is behind a proxy (a client-configured
        "classical application proxy", as defined in <xref target="RFC1919"/>,
        Section 3), but direct access to the Internet
        is also supported, WebRTC's STUN
        <xref target="RFC5389" />checks will bypass the proxy and reveal the
        public address of the client.</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Of these three concerns, #2 is the most significant concern, since for
      some users, the purpose of using a VPN is for anonymity. However,
      different VPN users will have different needs, and some VPN users (e.g.
      corporate VPN users) may in fact prefer WebRTC to send media traffic
      directly, i.e., not through the VPN.</t>
      <t>#3 is a less common concern, as proxy administrators can control this
      behavior through organization firewall policy if desired, coupled with the
      fact that forcing WebRTC traffic through a proxy will have negative
      effects on both the proxy and on media quality. For situations where this
      is an important consideration, use of a RETURN proxy, as described below,
      can be an effective solution.</t>
      <t>#1 is considered to be the least significant concern, given that the
      local address values often contain minimal information (e.g.
      192.168.0.2), or have built-in privacy protection (e.g.
      <xref target="RFC4941" />IPv6 addresses).</t>
      <t>Note also that these concerns predate WebRTC; Adobe Flash Player has
      provided similar functionality since the introduction of RTMFP
      <xref target="RFC7016" />in 2008.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Goals">
      <t>Being peer-to-peer, WebRTC represents a privacy-enabling technology,
      and therefore we want to avoid solutions that disable WebRTC or make it
      harder to use. This means that WebRTC should be configured by default to
      only reveal the minimum amount of information needed to establish a
      performant WebRTC session, while providing options to reveal additional
      information upon user consent, or further limit this information if the
      user has specifically requested this. Specifically, WebRTC should:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Provide a privacy-friendly default behavior which strikes the right
        balance between privacy and media performance for most users and use
        cases.</t>
        <t>For users who care more about one versus the other, provide a means
        to customize the experience.</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>
    <section title="Detailed Design">
      <t>The key principles for the design are listed below:
      <list style="numbers">
        <t>By default, WebRTC should follow normal IP routing rules, to the
        extent that this is easy to determine (i.e., not considering proxies).
        This can be accomplished by binding local sockets to the wildcard
        addresses (0.0.0.0 for IPv4, :: for IPv6), which allows the OS to route
        WebRTC traffic the same way as it would HTTP traffic, and allows only
        the 'typical' public addresses to be discovered.</t>
        <t>By default, support for direct connections between hosts (i.e.,
        without traversing a NAT or relay server) should be maintained. To
        accomplish this, the local IPv4 and IPv6 addresses of the interface
        used for outgoing STUN traffic should still be surfaced as candidates,
        even when binding to the wildcard addresses as mentioned above. The
        appropriate addresses here can be discovered by the common trick of
        binding sockets to the wildcard addresses, connect()ing those sockets
        to some well-known public IP address (one particular example being
        "8.8.8.8"), and then reading the bound local addresses via
        getsockname(). This approach requires no data exchange; it simply
        provides a mechanism for applications to retrieve the desired
        information from the kernel routing table.</t>
        <t>Determining whether a web proxy is in use is a complex process, as
        the answer can depend on the exact site or address being contacted.
        Furthermore, web proxies that support UDP are not widely deployed
        today. As a result, when WebRTC is made to go through a proxy, it
        typically needs to use TCP, either ICE-TCP
        <xref target="RFC6544" />or TURN-over-TCP
        <xref target="RFC5766" />. Naturally, this has attendant costs on media
        quality as well as proxy performance, and should be avoided where
        possible.</t>
        <t>RETURN
        <xref target="I-D.ietf-rtcweb-return" />is a proposal for explicit
        proxying of WebRTC media traffic. When RETURN proxies are deployed,
        media and STUN checks will go through the proxy, but without the
        performance issues associated with sending through a typical web
        proxy.</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Based on these ideas, we define four specific modes of WebRTC behavior,
      reflecting different media quality/privacy tradeoffs:
      <list style="format Mode %d:">
        <t>Enumerate all addresses: WebRTC MUST bind to all interfaces
        individually and use them all to attempt communication with STUN
        servers, TURN servers, or peers. This will converge on the best media
        path, and is ideal when media performance is the highest priority, but
        it discloses the most information.</t>
        <t>Default route + associated local addresses: WebRTC MUST follow the
        kernel routing table rules (e.g., by binding solely to the wildcard
        address), which will typically cause media packets to take the same
        route as the application's HTTP traffic. In addition, any private IPv4
        and IPv6 addresses associated with the kernel-chosen interface MUST
        be discovered through getsockname, as mentioned above, and provided
        to the application. This ensures that direct connections can still be
        established in this mode.</t>
        <t>Default route only: This is the the same as Mode 2, except that the
        associated private address MUST NOT be provided. This may cause traffic
        to hairpin through a NAT, fall back to the application TURN server, or
        fail altogether, with resulting quality implications.</t>
        <t>Force proxy: This forces all WebRTC media traffic through a proxy,
        if one is configured. If the proxy does not support UDP (as is the case
        for all HTTP and most SOCKS
        <xref target="RFC1928" />proxies), or the WebRTC implementation does
        not support UDP proxying, the use of UDP will be disabled, and TCP will
        be used to send and receive media through the proxy. Use of TCP will
        result in reduced quality, in addition to any performance
        considerations associated with sending all WebRTC media through the
        proxy server.</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Mode 1 MUST only be used when user consent has been provided; this
      thwarts the typical drive-by enumeration attacks. The details of this
      consent are left to the implementation; one potential mechanism is to tie
      this consent to getUserMedia consent.</t>
      <t>In cases where user consent has not been obtained, Mode 2 SHOULD be
      used. This allows applications to still achieve direct connections in many
      cases, even without consent (e.g., data channel applications). However,
      user agents MAY choose a stricter default policy in certain circumstances.
      </t>
      <t>Note that when a RETURN proxy is configured for the interface
      associated with the default route, Mode 2 and 3 will cause any external
      media traffic to go through the RETURN proxy. While the RETURN approach
      gives the best performance, a similar result can be achieved for
      non-RETURN proxies via an organization firewall policy that only allows
      external WebRTC traffic to leave through the proxy (typically, over TCP).
      This provides a way to ensure the proxy is used for any external traffic,
      but avoids the performance issues of Mode 4, where all media is forced
      through said proxy, for intra-organization traffic.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Application Guidance">
      <t>The recommendations mentioned in this document may cause certain
      WebRTC applications to malfunction. In order to be robust in all
      scenarios, the following guidelines are provided for applications:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Applications SHOULD deploy a TURN server with support for both UDP
        and TCP connections to the server. This ensures that connectivity can
        still be established, even when Mode 3 or 4 are in use, assuming the
        TURN server can be reached.</t>
        <t>Applications SHOULD detect when they don't have access to the full
        set of ICE candidates by checking for the presence of host candidates.
        If no host candidates are present, Mode 3 or 4 above is in use; this
        knowledge can be useful for diagnostic purposes.</t>
        <t>Future versions of browsers may present an indicator to signify that
        the page is using WebRTC to set up a peer-to-peer connection.
        Applications MUST only use WebRTC in a fashion that is
        consistent with user expectations.</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>This document is entirely devoted to security considerations.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requires no actions from IANA.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Several people provided input into this document, including
      Harald Alvestrand, Ted Hardie, Matthew Kaufmann, Eric Rescorla,
      Adam Roach, and Martin Thomson.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119.xml'?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1918.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1919.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.1928.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4941.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5245.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5389.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.5766.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6544.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7016.xml'?>
      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.ietf-rtcweb-return.xml'?>
    </references>
    <section title="Change log">
      <t>Changes in draft -03:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Clarified when to use which modes.</t>
        <t>Use 2119 qualifiers to make normative statements.</t>
        <t>Defined 'proxy'.</t>
        <t>Mentioned split tunnels in problem statement.</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Changes in draft -02:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Recommendations -&gt; Requirements</t>
        <t>Updated text regarding consent.</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Changes in draft -01:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Incorporated feedback from Adam Roach; changes to discussion of
        cam/mic permission, as well as use of proxies, and various editorial
        changes.</t>
        <t>Added several more references.</t>
      </list></t>
      <t>Changes in draft -00:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>Published as WG draft.</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
