<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5245 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5245.xml">
<!ENTITY icemob SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.wing-mmusic-ice-mobility.xml">
<!ENTITY mprtp SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.singh-avtcore-mprtp.xml">
<!ENTITY redirect SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.williams-peer-redirect.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc colonspace="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="no" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-uberti-mmusic-nombis-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="IceNom">Improvements to ICE Candidate Nomination</title>

    <author fullname="Justin Uberti" initials="J." surname="Uberti">
      <organization>Google</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>747 6th Ave S</street>

          <city>Kirkland</city>

          <region>WA</region>

          <code>98033</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>justin@uberti.name</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jonathan Lennox" initials="J." surname="Lennox">
      <organization>Vidyo</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>433 Hackensack Avenue</street>

          <city>Hackensack</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07601</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jonathan@vidyo.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="06" month="November" year="2014" />

    <area>RAI</area>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document makes recommendations for simplifying and improving the
      procedures for candidate nomination in Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE).</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>Interactive Connectivity Establishment (ICE) attempts to find the 'best'
      path for connectivity between two peers; in ICE parlance, these paths are
      known as 'candidate pairs'. During the ICE process, one endpoint,
      known as the 'controlling' endpoint, selects a candidate pair as the 
      best pair; this action is known as nomination. ICE supports two different
      mechanisms for performing nomination, known as Regular Nomination, and
      Aggressive Nomination.</t>
      <t>However, each of these modes have flaws that restrict their usefulness.
      Regular Nomination, as currently speced, requires a best pair to be chosen
      before media transmission can start, causing unnecessary call setup delay.
      Aggressive Nomination, while avoiding this delay, gives the controlling
      endpoint much less discretion into which candidate pair is chosen, preventing
      it from making decisions based on dynamic factors such as RTT or loss rate.
      Needless to say, the presence of both modes also adds nontrivial complexity.</t>
      <t>Lastly, ICE is currently defined as a finite process, where the decision on
      the optimal candidate pair is made during call setup and infrequently (if ever)
      changed. While this may be acceptable for endpoints with static network 
      configurations, it fails to meet the needs of mobile endpoints, who may need
      to seamlessly move between networks, or be connected to multiple networks
      simultaneously. In these cases, the controlling endpoint may want to maintain
      multiple potential candidate pairs, and make dynamic decisions to switch 
      between them as conditions change.</t>
      <t>To address these challenges, this document makes two proposals for 
      refactoring ICE nomination - merging Regular and Aggressive Nomination, and 
      introducing a new mode, known as Continuous Nomination. This makes ICE
      substantially more flexible without increasing complexity.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Goals and Requirements">
      <t>The goals for improved ICE nomination are enumerated below.</t>
      <section title="Minimize Call Setup Latency" anchor="minimize-latency">
          <t>Modern ICE agents will often have multiple network interfaces and
          multiple servers from which to obtain ICE candidates. While some ICE checks
          may succeed quickly, finishing the entire set of checks can easily take multiple
          seconds. As a result, ICE endpoints MUST be able to start transmitting
          media immediately upon a successful ICE check, and MUST retain the ability
          to switch if a better candidate pair becomes available later.
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Allow Controlling Endpoint to Make Dynamic Decisions" anchor="dynamic-decisions">
          <t>While an ICE endpoint will assign various priority values to its ICE candidates,
          these priorities are static and can only be based on a priori knowledge. To 
          properly make choices in multi-network and multi-server scenarios, the controlling
          endpoint MUST be able to make dynamic decisions about the selected candidate pair
          based on observed network performance. To ensure symmetric flows, this implies that
          the controlling endpoint MUST be able to communicate its choice to the controlled
          side.       
          </t>
      </section>
       <section title="Allow Selected Pair Change At Any Time Without Signaling" anchor="continuous-change">
          <t>Expanding on the requirement above, the need to make dynamic decisions is not
          limited to call setup. A multihomed endpoint may need to switch interfaces based on
          mobility considerations, or a robust endpoint may want to keep multiple network paths
          warm and switch immediately if connectivity is interrupted on one of them. As the
          signaling channel may be affected by the event necessitating the switch, this
          implies that the controlling endpoint MUST be able to change the selected pair
          and indicate this to the remote side without signaling.
          </t>
          <t>The rules in <xref target="RFC5245" /> ensure that the controlled
          endpoint keeps its candidate needed for the selected pair alive. However,
          in order for alternate pairs to remain available, the controlled endpoint 
          must keep the associated candidates alive
          as well. This implies that the controlling endpoint MUST have some way to 
          indicate to the controlled side that specific candidates are to be kept alive.
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Allow Continuous Addition of Candidates" anchor="continuous-candidates">
          <t>In certain network mobility scenarios, networks may come up and down
          while the call is active. In order to allow candidates gathered on these 
          networks to be used for the selected pair or backup pairs, the endpoint MUST
          be able to gather candidates on these networks and communicate them to the
          remote side. While this could be done using an ICE restart, as described in
          <xref target="RFC5245" />, the ICE restart implies that these candidates
          should replace, instead of add to, the previously exchanged candidates.
          [TODO: should this just be a tweak to Trickle ICE? It's not really specific
          to nomination.]         
          </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Maintain Backwards Compatibility" anchor="maintain-backcompat">
          <t>To prevent interoperability problems, ICE endpoints that support the
          functionality listed above MUST still maintain <xref target="RFC5245"/> compliance
          when interacting with existing endpoints. However, the ideal solution SHOULD
          allow some improvements to occur when only the controlling side supports the new
          functionality.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Minimize Complexity Increase" anchor="minimize-complexity">
          <t>Increased functionality typically leads to increased complexity, which
          leads to more edge cases, and more implementation bugs. This suggests that
          in addition to proposing new ICE functionality, the ideal solution SHOULD 
          deprecate superfluous functionality.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Deprecating Aggressive Nomination">
      <section title="Overview">
        <t>The main benefits of Regular Nomination are that the controlling side can
         dynamically choose which candidate pair to use, and a clear signal when the
         nomination process has completed, via the presence of the USE-CANDIDATE flag
         in a Binding Request. The main benefit of Aggressive Nomination is that it is
         only necessary to send a single Binding Request before starting the transmission
         of media, reducing setup latency. Why don't we have both?
        </t>
        <t>
        By preserving the dynamic behavior of Regular Nomination, but allowing media
        transmission to start upon a single successful connectivity check,
        as in Aggressive Nomination, the requirements of <xref target="minimize-latency"/>
        and <xref target="dynamic-decisions"/> can be met, while meeting the compatibility
        requirement from <xref target="maintain-backcompat" /> and, since
        Aggressive Nomination is no longer needed, the complexity requirement from 
        <xref target="minimize-complexity" />.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Operation">
        <t>Since media may be transmitted as soon as all components have a valid pair,
        as indicated in <xref target="RFC5245" />, Page 69, an ICE Agent can begin
        transmitting media as soon as this occurs, even if it has not sent a Binding
        Request with USE-CANDIDATE.</t>
        <t>This pair can change as more pairs are added to the Valid list on the controlling side. When
nomination completes, and a final pair is selected, this is communicated to the controlled side
via the typical Binding Request with USE-CANDIDATE.</t>
        <t>On the controlled side, the same process can occur, with the ICE Agent transmitting media as
soon as a valid pair exists. To encourage use of symmetric RTP, the controlled ICE Agent
SHOULD use the same candidate pair on which it received media from the controlling side.
[Doesn't need to be secure media, since the controlling side will finalize this preference
through USE-CANDIDATE shortly.]</t>
        <t>As this is legal ICE behavior, no negotiation of this mechanism should be needed. In the
event the receiver drops any packets that arrive before a Binding Request with
USE-CANDIDATE set, this will simply lead to brief media clipping and will resolve itself once
nomination completes.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Backwards Compatibility">
        <t>When acting in the controlled role, new implementations MUST not use
        Aggressive Nomination.</t>
        <t>When acting in the controlled role, and the controlling side is using
        Aggressive Nomination (e.g. sending USE-CANDIDATE in its initial Binding Requests),
        the standard PRIORITY-based mechanism outlined in [TODO] should be used to
        determine the reverse media path.
        </t>
        <t>Note that if implementations would prefer to just avoid Aggressive Nomination
        altogether, they MAY indicate some TBD pseudo-option in the ice-options attribute.
        Because compliant implementations MUST NOT use Aggressive Nomination if an unknown
        ICE option is encountered, this effectively prohibits the use of Aggressive Nomination.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Introducing Continuous Nomination">
      <section title="Overview">
        <t>As discussed above, in mobile environments there can be multiple possible
        valid candidate pairs, and  these can change at various points in the call, 
        as new interfaces go up and down, signal strength for wireless interfaces changes,
        and new relay servers are discovered.</t>
        <t>However, under 5245 rules, once a candidate pair is selected and confirmed, via
USE-CANDIDATE, nomination has completed and cannot be restarted without performing an
ICE restart. This is overly complex in many cases, and especially problematic in some specific
ones, namely a wifi-cellular handover, where the signaling path for communicating an ICE restart
may be impacted by the handover.</t>
        <t>To address this situation, this section introduces the concept of "continuous nomination",
        where the controlling ICE endpoint can adjust the selected candidate pair at any time.
        By allowing ICE processing to occur continuously during a call, rather than just at call
        setup, the requirements expressed in <xref target="continuous-change"/> and
        <xref target="continuous-candidates"/> can be met.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Operation">
        
        <t>Upon receipt of a Binding Request with USE-CANDIDATE, the controlled side MUST switch
its media path to the candidate pair on which the Binding Request was received. [could also
follow media, if secure]</t>
        <t>During continuous nomination, the controlling side may still elect to prune certain candidate
pairs; for example, an implementation may choose to drop relay candidates once a successful
connection has been established. The controlling ICE Agent does this by continuing to send
Binding Requests to the remote side on each candidate pair that it still wants to retain. The
controlled ICE Agent SHOULD prune any candidate pairs that have not received a Binding
Request in N seconds (30?), and SHOULD NOT keep alive any candidates that are not
associated with a live candidate pair. One side benefit of doing this is that the continuous
exchange of Binding Requests across all candidate pairs allows the RTT and loss rate for
each to be reliably determined and kept up to date.</t>
        <t>At any point, either side may perform an ICE restart, which will result in both sides gathering
new ICE candidates, starting a new continuous nomination sequence, and upon successful
completion, discarding all candidates from the previous nomination sequence.</t>
      </section> 
      <section title="Backwards Compatibility">
        <t>Under continuous nomination, ICE never concludes; new candidates can always be trickled,
and a new candidate pair can always be selected by the controlling side by sending a new
Binding Request with a USE-CANDIDATE attribute. The decision about which candidate pair
to use is fully dynamic; the controlled side can use metrics such as RTT or loss rate to
change the selected pair at any time.</t>
        <t>Since standard ICE implementations may not expect the selected pair to change after a
USE-CANDIDATE attribute is received, support for continuous nomination is explicitly
indicated via a new "continuous" value for ice-options. If the remote side does not support the
"continuous" option, the controlling side MUST fall back to Regular Nomination [consistent
        with the behavior specified in TBD].</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations">
      <t>TODO</t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requires no actions from IANA.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Several people provided significant input into this document, including Martin Thomson, Brandon Williams, and Dan Wing.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc5245;
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      &redirect;
      &icemob;
      &mprtp;
    </references>

    <section title="Change log">
      <t>Changes in draft -00: <list style="symbols">
        <t>Initial version, from mailing list discussion post-IETF 90.</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
