<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3550 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4585 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4585.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5104 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5104.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5234 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6190 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6190.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7656 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7656.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7741 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7741.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7798 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7798.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc8082 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8082.xml">
<!ENTITY vp9rtp SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-payload-vp9.xml">
<!ENTITY framemarking SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-avtext-framemarking.xml">

]>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-avtext-lrr-06" ipr="trust200902">
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>

  <?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>

  <!-- alphabetize the references -->

  <?rfc comments="no"?>

  <!-- show comments -->

  <?rfc inline="yes" ?>

  <!-- comments are inline -->

  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>

  <!-- generate table of contents -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Layer Refresh Request RTCP Feedback">The Layer Refresh Request (LRR) RTCP Feedback Message</title>

    <author fullname="Jonathan Lennox" initials="J." surname="Lennox">
      <organization abbrev="Vidyo">Vidyo, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>433 Hackensack Avenue</street>

          <street>Seventh Floor</street>

          <city>Hackensack</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07601</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jonathan@vidyo.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

     <author fullname="Danny Hong" initials="D." surname="Hong">
      <organization abbrev="Vidyo">Vidyo, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>433 Hackensack Avenue</street>

          <street>Seventh Floor</street>

          <city>Hackensack</city>

          <region>NJ</region>

          <code>07601</code>

          <country>US</country>
        </postal>

        <email>danny@vidyo.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Justin Uberti" initials="J." surname="Uberti">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Google, Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>747 6th Street South</street>

          <city>Kirkland</city>

          <region>WA</region>

          <code>98033</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>justin@uberti.name</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Stefan Holmer" initials="S." surname="Holmer">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Google, Inc.</organization>
       <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kungsbron 2</street>

          <code>111 22</code>

          <city>Stockholm</city>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
		<email>holmer@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Magnus Flodman" initials="M." surname="Flodman">
      <organization abbrev="Google">Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Kungsbron 2</street>

          <code>111 22</code>

          <city>Stockholm</city>

          <country>Sweden</country>
        </postal>
		<email>mflodman@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <area>RAI</area>

    <workgroup>Payload Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>RFC</keyword>

    <keyword>Request for Comments</keyword>

    <keyword>RTP</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This memo describes the RTCP Payload-Specific Feedback Message
		"Layer Refresh Request" (LRR), which can be used to request a
		state refresh of one or more substreams of a layered media
		stream.  It also defines its use with several RTP payloads for
		scalable media formats.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This memo describes an <xref target="RFC3550">RTCP</xref> <xref target="RFC4585">Payload-Specific Feedback Message</xref>
		"Layer Refresh Request" (LRR).  It is designed to allow a
		receiver of a layered media stream to request that one or more
		of its substreams be refreshed, such that it can then be
		decoded by an endpoint which previously was not receiving those
		layers, without requiring that the
		entire stream be refreshed (as it would be if the receiver
		sent a <xref target='RFC5104'>Full Intra Request (FIR); </xref>
		see also <xref target='RFC8082' />).</t>

	  <t>The feedback message is applicable both to temporally
	  and spatially scaled streams, and to both single-stream and
	  multi-stream scalability modes.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="conventions"
             title="Conventions, Definitions and Acronyms">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/>.</t>


	<section anchor="terminology"
			 title="Terminology">
	  <t>A "Layer Refresh Point" is a point in a scalable stream after
	  which a decoder, which previously had been able to decode only some
	  (possibly none) of the available layers of stream, is able to
	  decode a greater number of the layers.</t>

	  <t>For spatial (or quality) layers, layer refresh typically
	  requires that a spatial layer be encoded in a way that
	  references only lower-layer subpictures of the current picture,
	  not any earlier pictures of that spatial layer.  Additionally,
	  the encoder must promise that no earlier pictures of that
	  spatial layer will be used as reference in the future.</t>

	  <t>In a layer refresh, however, other layers than the ones
	  requested for refresh may still maintain dependency on earlier
	  content of the stream.  This is the difference between a layer
	  refresh and a <xref target='RFC5104'>Full Intra
	  Request</xref>.  This minimizes the coding overhead of refresh
	  to only those parts of the stream that actually need to be
	  refreshed at any given time.</t>

      <figure anchor="figureSpatialRefreshEnhanced">
        <preamble>An illustration of spatial layer refresh of an
        enhancement layer is shown below.</preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
     ... <--  S1  <--  S1       S1  <--  S1  <-- ...
               |        |        |        |
              \/       \/       \/       \/
     ... <--  S0  <--  S0  <--  S0  <--  S0  <-- ...

               1        2        3        4
          ]]></artwork>

      </figure>

      <t>In <xref target='figureSpatialRefreshEnhanced'/>, frame 3 is a layer refresh
			point for spatial layer S1; a decoder which had previously
			only been decoding spatial layer S0 would be able to
			decode layer S1 starting at frame 3.</t>

      <figure anchor="figureSpatialRefreshBase">
        <preamble>An illustration of spatial layer refresh of a base layer is shown
        below.</preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
     ... <--  S1  <--  S1  <--  S1  <--  S1  <-- ...
               |        |        |        |
              \/       \/       \/       \/
     ... <--  S0  <--  S0       S0  <--  S0  <-- ...

               1        2        3        4
          ]]></artwork>

      </figure>

      <t>In <xref target="figureSpatialRefreshBase"/>, frame 3 is a layer refresh
		point for spatial layer S0; a decoder which had previously
		not been decoding the stream at all could decode layer S0
		starting at frame 3.</t>

	  <t>For temporal layers, layer refresh requires that the layer be
	  "temporally nested", i.e. use as reference only
	  earlier frames of a lower temporal layer, not any earlier frames of this
	  temporal layer, and also promise that no future frames
	  of this temporal layer will reference frames of this temporal
	  layer before the refresh point.  In many cases, the temporal
	  structure of the stream will mean that all frames are
	  temporally nested, in which case decoders will have no need to
	  send LRR messages for the stream.</t>

      <figure anchor="figureTemporalRefresh">
        <preamble>An illustration of temporal layer refresh is shown
        below.</preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
        ...  <----- T1  <------ T1          T1  <------ ...
                   /           /           /
                 |_          |_          |_
     ... <--  T0  <------ T0  <------ T0  <------ T0  <--- ...

               1     2     3     4     5     6     7
          ]]></artwork>
      </figure>

      <t>In <xref target="figureTemporalRefresh"/>, frame 6 is a layer refresh
		point for temporal layer T1; a decoder which had previously
		only been decoding temporal layer T0 would be able to
		decode layer T1 starting at frame 6.</t>

      <figure anchor="figureTemporalNesting">
        <preamble>An illustration of an inherently temporally nested
        stream is shown below.</preamble>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                    T1          T1          T1
                   /           /           /
                 |_          |_          |_
     ... <--  T0  <------ T0  <------ T0  <------ T0  <--- ...

               1     2     3     4     5     6     7
          ]]></artwork>

      </figure>

      <t>In <xref target="figureTemporalNesting"/>, the stream is temporally
        nested in its ordinary structure; a decoder receiving layer
        T0 can begin decoding layer T1 at any point.</t>

	  <t>A "Layer Index" is a numeric label for a specific spatial and
	  temporal layer of a scalable stream.  It
	  consists of the pair of a "temporal ID" identifying the temporal
	  layer, and a "layer ID" identifying the spatial or quality
	  layer.  The details of how layers of a scalable stream are labeled are
	  codec-specific.  Details for several codecs are defined in
	  <xref target="codec-details"/>.</t>

	</section>

    </section>

	<section anchor="layerRefreshRequest" title="Layer Refresh Request">
	  <t>A layer refresh frame can be requested by sending a Layer Refresh Request (LRR),
	  which is an <xref target="RFC3550">RTP Control Protocol (RTCP)</xref>
	  <xref target="RFC4585">payload-specific feedback message</xref> asking the encoder to encode a frame
	  which makes it possible to upgrade to a higher layer. The LRR
	  contains one or two tuples, indicating the temporal and spatial layer the decoder
	  wants to upgrade to, and (optionally) the currently highest
	  temporal and spatial 
	  layer the decoder can decode.</t>

	  <t>The specific format of the tuples, and the mechanism by which
	  a receiver recognizes a refresh frame, is
	  codec-dependent.  Usage for several codecs is discussed in
	  <xref target="codec-details"/>.</t>

	  <t>LRR follows the model of the <xref target="RFC5104">Full
	  Intra Request (FIR)</xref> (Section 3.5.1) for its
	  retransmission, reliability, and use in multipoint conferences.</t>

	  <t>The LRR message is identified by RTCP packet type value
	  PT=PSFB and FMT=TBD.  The FCI field MUST contain one or more LRR entries.  Each entry
   applies to a different media sender, identified by its SSRC.</t>

	  <t>[NOTE TO RFC Editor: Please replace "TBD" with the IANA-assigned payload-specific feedback
		number.]</t>

	  <section anchor="MessageFormat" title="Message Format">

		<t>The Feedback Control Information (FCI) for the Layer Refresh Request
		  consists of one or more FCI entries, the content of which is
   depicted in <xref target="figureFciFormat"/>.  The length of
		  the LRR feedback message MUST be set to
   2+3*N, where N is the number of FCI entries.</t>

      <figure anchor="figureFciFormat">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
    0                   1                   2                   3
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |                              SSRC                             |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | Seq nr.       |C| Payload Type| Reserved                      |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   | RES     | TTID| TLID          | RES     | CTID| CLID (opt)    |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          ]]></artwork>
	  </figure>

	  <t>
		<list style="hanging">
		  <t hangText="SSRC (32 bits)"> The SSRC value of the media sender that is
              requested to send a layer refresh point.</t>

		  <t hangText="Seq nr. (8 bits)"> Command sequence number.  The sequence number
              space is unique for each pairing of the SSRC of command
              source and the SSRC of the command target.  The sequence
              number SHALL be increased by 1 modulo 256 for each new
              command.  A repetition SHALL NOT increase the sequence
              number.  The initial value is arbitrary.</t>

		  <t hangText="C (1 bit)">A flag bit indicating whether the
			"Current Temporal Layer ID (CTID)" and "Current Layer ID
			(CLID)" fields are present in the FCI.  If
			this bit is 0, the sender of the LRR message is
			requesting refresh of all layers up to and including the
			target layer.</t>

		  <t hangText="Payload Type (7 bits)">The RTP payload type for
		  which the LRR is being requested.  This gives the context in
		  which the target layer index is to be interpreted.</t>

		  <t hangText="Reserved (RES) (16 bits / 5 bits / 5 bits)"> All bits SHALL be set to 0
			by the sender and SHALL be ignored on reception.</t>

		  <t hangText="Target Temporal Layer ID (TTID) (3 bits)">The temporal ID
			of the target layer for which the receiver wishes a refresh point.</t>

		  <t hangText="Target Layer ID (TLID) (8 bits)">The layer ID of the target spatial or quality
			layer
			for which the receiver wishes a refresh point.  Its format
			is dependent on the payload type field.</t>

		  <t hangText="Current Temporal Layer ID (CTID) (3 bits)">If C is 1,
			the ID of the current temporal layer being decoded by the receiver. 
			This message is not requesting refresh of layers at or below this layer.
			If C is 0, this field SHALL be set to 0 by the sender and
			SHALL be ignored on reception.</t>

		  <t hangText="Current Layer ID (CLID) (8 bits)">If C is 1, the
		  layer ID of the current spatial or quality layer being decoded by the receiver.  This message
		  is not requesting refresh of layers at or below this layer.
		  If C is 0, this field SHALL be set to 0 by the sender and
		  SHALL be ignored on reception.</t>
		</list>
	  </t>

	  <t>When C is 1, TTID MUST NOT be less than CTID, and TLID
	  MUST NOT be less than CLID; at least one of TTID or TLID MUST be greater
	  than CTID or CLID respectively.  That is to say, the target layer index &lt;TTID,
	  TLID&gt; MUST be a layer upgrade from the current layer index &lt;CTID, CLID&gt;.
	  A sender MAY request an upgrade in both temporal and
	  spatial/quality layers simultaneously.</t>

	  <t>Note: the syntax of the TTID, TLID, CTID, and CLID fields 
	  match, by design, the TID and LID fields in
	  <xref target='I-D.ietf-avtext-framemarking' />.</t>

	  </section>

	  <section title="Semantics">

		<t>Within the common packet header for feedback messages (as defined in
   section 6.1 of <xref target='RFC4585' />), the "SSRC of packet sender" field
   indicates the source of the request, and the "SSRC of media source"
   is not used and SHALL be set to 0.  The SSRCs of the media senders to
   which the LRR command applies are in the corresponding FCI entries.
   A LRR message MAY contain requests to multiple media senders, using
   one FCI entry per target media sender.</t>

   <t>Upon reception of LRR, the encoder MUST send a decoder refresh point
   (see <xref target='terminology' />) as soon as possible.</t>

   <t>The sender MUST respect bandwidth limits provided by the
	 application of congestion control, as described in Section 5 of
	 <xref target='RFC5104' />.  As layer refresh points will often be
	 larger than non-refreshing frames, this may restrict a sender's
	 ability to send a layer refresh point quickly.</t>

	  </section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="codec-details" title="Usage with specific codecs">

	  <t>In order for LRR to be used with a scalable codec, the format
	  of the temporal and layer ID fields (for both the target and
	  current layer indices) needs to be
	  specified for that codec's RTP packetization.  New RTP
	  packetization specifications for scalable codecs SHOULD define
	  how this is done. (The <xref target='I-D.ietf-payload-vp9'>VP9
	  payload</xref>, for instance, has done so.)  If the payload also
	  specifies how it is used with
	  <xref target='I-D.ietf-avtext-framemarking'>the Frame Marking
		RTP Header Extension</xref>, the syntax MUST be defined
		in the same manner as the TID and LID fields in that header.</t>

	  <section title="H264 SVC">

		<t><xref target="RFC6190">H.264 SVC</xref> defines temporal,
		dependency (spatial), and quality scalability modes.</t>

		<figure anchor="figureH264SvcIndexFormat">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            +---------------+---------------+
            |0|1|2|3|4|5|6|7|0|1|2|3|4|5|6|7|
            +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            | RES     | TID |R|  DID  | QID |
            +---------------+---------------+
          ]]></artwork>
		</figure>

		<t><xref target="figureH264SvcIndexFormat"/> shows the format
		of the layer index fields for H.264 SVC streams.  The "R" and "RES"
		fields MUST be set to 0 on transmission and ignored on
		reception.  See <xref target='RFC6190'/> Section 1.1.3 for
		details on the DID, QID, and TID fields.</t>

		<t>A dependency or quality layer refresh of a given layer in
		H.264 SVC can be identified by the "I" bit (idr_flag) in the
		extended NAL unit header, present in NAL unit types 14 (prefix
		NAL unit) and 20 (coded scalable slice).  Layer refresh of the
		base layer can also be identified by its NAL unit type of
		its coded slices, which is "5" rather than "1".  A dependency or
		quality layer refresh is complete once this bit has been seen
		on all the appropriate layers (in decoding order) above the
		current layer index (if any, or beginning from the base layer
		if not) through the target layer index.</t>

		<t>Note that as the "I" bit in a PACSI header is set if the
		corresponding bit is set in any of the aggregated NAL units it
		describes; thus, it is not sufficient to identify layer
		refresh when NAL units of multiple dependency or quality layers
		are aggregated.</t>

		<t>In H.264 SVC, temporal layer refresh information can be
		determined from various Supplemental Encoding Information
		(SEI) messages in the bitstream.</t>

		<t>Whether an H.264 SVC stream is scalably nested can be determined from
		the Scalability Information SEI message's temporal_id_nesting
		flag.  If this flag is set in a stream's currently applicable
		Scalability Information SEI, receivers SHOULD NOT send
		temporal LRR messages for that stream, as every frame is
		implicitly a temporal layer refresh point.  (The Scalability
		Information SEI message may also be available in the signaling
		negotiation of H.264 SVC, as the sprop-scalability-info
		parameter.)</t>

		<t>If a stream's temporal_id_nesting flag is not set, the
		Temporal Level Switching Point SEI message identifies temporal
		layer switching points.  A temporal layer refresh is satisfied
		when this SEI message is present in a frame with the target
		layer index, if the message's delta_frame_num refers to a frame
		with the requested current layer index.  (Alternately,
		temporal layer refresh can also be satisfied by a complete
		state refresh, such as an IDR.)  Senders which support
		receiving LRR for non-temporally-nested streams MUST insert
		Temporal Level Switching Point SEI messages as appropriate.</t>

	  </section>

	  <section title="VP8">

		<t><xref target="RFC7741">The VP8 RTP payload
		format</xref> defines temporal scalability modes.  It does not
		support spatial scalability.</t>

		<figure anchor="figureVP8IndexFormat">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            +---------------+---------------+
            |0|1|2|3|4|5|6|7|0|1|2|3|4|5|6|7|
            +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            | RES     | TID | RES           |
            +---------------+---------------+
          ]]></artwork>
		</figure>

		<t><xref target="figureVP8IndexFormat"/> shows the format
		of the layer index field for VP8 streams.  The "RES"
		fields MUST be set to 0 on transmission and be ignored on
		reception.  See <xref target='RFC7741'/> Section 4.2 for
		details on the TID field.</t>

		<t>A VP8 layer refresh point can be identified by the presence
		of the "Y" bit in the VP8 payload header.  When this bit is
		set, this and all subsequent frames depend only on the current
		base temporal layer.  On receipt of an LRR for a VP8 stream, A
		sender which supports LRR MUST encode the stream so it can set the
		Y bit in a packet whose temporal layer is at or below the target
		layer index.</t>

		<t>Note that in VP8, not every layer switch point can be
		identified by the Y bit, since the Y bit implies layer switch
		of all layers, not just the layer in which it is sent.  Thus
		the use of LRR with VP8 can result in some inefficiency in
		transmision.  However, this is not expected to be a major
		issue for temporal structures in normal use.</t> 

	  </section>

	  <section title="H265">

		<t>The initial version
		of <xref target="RFC7798">the H.265 payload
		format</xref> defines temporal scalability, with protocol
		elements reserved for spatial or other scalability modes
		(which are expected to be defined in a future version of the
		specification).</t>

		<figure anchor="figureH265IndexFormat">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
            +---------------+---------------+
            |0|1|2|3|4|5|6|7|0|1|2|3|4|5|6|7|
            +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            | RES     | TID |RES|  LayerId  |
            +---------------+---------------+
          ]]></artwork>
		</figure>

		<t><xref target="figureH265IndexFormat"/> shows the format
		of the layer index field for H.265 streams.  The "RES"
		fields MUST be set to 0 on transmission and ignored on
		reception.  See <xref target='RFC7798'/> Section 1.1.4 for
		details on the LayerId and TID fields.</t>

		<t>H.265 streams signal whether they are temporally nested,
		using the vps_temporal_id_nesting_flag in the Video Parameter
		Set (VPS), and the sps_temporal_id_nesting_flag in the Sequence
		Parameter Set (SPS).  If this flag is set in a stream's currently applicable
		VPS or SPS, receivers SHOULD NOT send temporal LRR messages
		for that stream, as every frame is implicitly a temporal layer
		refresh point.</t>

		<t>If a stream's sps_temporal_id_nesting_flag is not set, the
		NAL unit types 2 to 5 inclusively identify temporal
		layer switching points.  A layer refresh to any higher
		target temporal layer is satisfied when a NAL unit type of 4 or 5 
		with TID equal to 1 more than current TID is seen.  Alternatively,
		layer refresh to a target temporal layer can be incrementally 
		satisfied with NAL unit type of 2 or 3.  In this case, given 
		current TID = TO and target TID = TN, layer refresh to TN is satisfied
		when NAL unit type of 2 or 3 is seen for TID = T1, then TID = T2, 
		all the way up to TID = TN.  During this incremental process, layer
		refresh to TN can be completely satisfied as soon as a NAL unit type
		of 2 or 3 is seen.</t>

		<t>Of course, temporal layer refresh can also be satisfied whenever 
		any Intra Random Access Point (IRAP) NAL unit type (with values 16-23,
		inclusively) is seen.  An IRAP picture is similar to an IDR picture in
		H.264 (NAL unit type of 5 in H.264) where decoding of the picture can start
		without any older pictures.</t>

		<t>In the (future) H.265 payloads that support spatial
		scalability, a spatial layer refresh of a specific layer can
		be identified by NAL units with the requested layer ID and NAL
		unit types between 16 and 21 inclusive.  A dependency or
		quality layer refresh is complete once NAL units of this type have been seen
		on all the appropriate layers (in decoding order) above the
		current layer index (if any, or beginning from the base layer
		if not) through the target layer index.</t>
	  </section>

	</section>

	<section title="Usage with different scalability transmission mechanisms">

	  <t>Several different mechanisms are defined for how scalable
	  streams can be transmitted in RTP.
	  The <xref target="RFC7656">RTP
	  Taxonomy</xref> Section 3.7 defines three mechanisms: Single RTP
	  Stream on a Single Media Transport (SRST), Multiple RTP Streams
	  on a Single Media Transport (MRST), and Multiple RTP Streams on
	  Multiple Media Transports (MRMT).</t>

	  <t>The LRR message is applicable to all these mechanisms.  For
	  MRST and MRMT mechanisms, the "media source" field of the LRR
	  FCI is set to the SSRC of the RTP stream containing the layer
	  indicated by the Current Layer Index (if "C" is 1), or the
	  stream containing the base encoded stream (if "C" is 0).  For
	  MRMT, it is sent on the RTP session on which this stream is
	  sent.  On receipt, the sender MUST refresh all the layers
	  requested in the stream, simultaneously in decode order.</t>

	</section>

    <section anchor="securityConsiderations" title="Security Considerations">
	  <t>All the security considerations of <xref target="RFC5104">FIR
	  feedback packets</xref> apply to LRR feedback packets as well.
	  Additionally, media senders receiving LRR feedback packets MUST
	  validate that the payload types and layer indices they are
	  receiving are valid for the stream they are currently sending,
	  and discard the requests if not.</t>
    </section>


	<section title="SDP Definitions">

	  <t>Section 7 of <xref target='RFC5104' /> defines SDP procedures
	  for indicating and negotiating support for codec control
	  messages (CCM) in SDP.  This document extends this with a new
	  codec control command, "lrr", which indicates support of the
	  Layer Refresh Request (LRR).</t>

	  <t><xref target='lrr_grammar' /> gives a formal
	  <xref target='RFC5234'>Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF)</xref>
	  showing this grammar extension, extending the grammar defined in
	  <xref target='RFC5104'/>.</t>

<figure anchor="lrr_grammar" title="Syntax of the &quot;lrr&quot;
ccm">
<artwork type="abnf">
rtcp-fb-ccm-param =/ SP "lrr"    ; Layer Refresh Request
</artwork>
</figure>

	  <t>The Offer-Answer considerations defined in
	  <xref target='RFC5104' /> Section 7.2 apply.</t>
	</section>

    <section anchor="IANAConsiderations" title="IANA Considerations">
	  <t>This document defines a new entry to the "Codec Control
	  Messages" subregistry of the "Session Description Protocol (SDP)
	  Parameters" registry, according to the following data:</t>
		
	  <t>
		<list style='hanging'>
		  <t hangText='Value name:'>lrr</t>
		  <t hangText='Long name:'>Layer Refresh Request Command</t>
		  <t hangText='Usable with:'>ccm</t>
		  <t hangText='Reference:'>RFC &rfc.number;</t>
		</list>
	  </t>

	  <t>This document also defines a new entry to the "FMT Values for
	  PSFB Payload Types" subregistry of the "Real-Time Transport
	  Protocol (RTP) Parameters" registry, according to the following
	  data:</t>

	  <t>
		<list style='hanging'>
		  <t hangText='Name:'>LRR</t>
		  <t hangText='Long Name:'>Layer Refresh Request Command</t>
		  <t hangText='Value:'>TBD</t>
		  <t hangText='Reference:'>RFC &rfc.number;</t>
		</list>
	  </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title='Normative References'>
      &rfc2119;

	  &rfc3550;

      &rfc4585;

	  &rfc5104;

	  &rfc5234;

	  &rfc6190;

	  &rfc7741;

	  &rfc7798;

	  &framemarking;
    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>

	  &rfc7656;

	  &rfc8082;

	  &vp9rtp;

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
<!--  LocalWords:  PictureID DCT Hadamard WHT SSRC CSRC pyld hdr FI VER RPSI
 -->
<!--  LocalWords:  stPartitionSize SLI SDP AVPF SRTP IANA PID PICIDX TID
 -->
